You've heard of your I.Q., your general intelligence,
لقد عرفتم نتيجة اختبار نسبة ذكائكم (IQ)،
but what's your Psy-Q?
ولكن ماذا عن اختباركم في (Psy-Q)؟
How much do you know about what makes you tick,
كم تعلمون عن الأمور التي تجعلكم تندهشون،
and how good are you at predicting other people's behavior
وكم تجيدون التنبؤ بتصرفات الآخرين
or even your own?
أو حتى تصرفاتكم؟
And how much of what you think you know about psychology is wrong?
وكم من الأشياء التي تعتقدون أنكم تعرفونها عن علم النفس خاطئة؟
Let's find out by counting down the top 10 myths of psychology.
دعونا نكتشف ذلك ونعد أكبر 10خرافات في علم النفس.
You've probably heard it said that when it comes to their psychology,
لعلكم سمعتم بأنه عندما يأتي الحديث عن نفسياتهم،
it's almost as if men are from Mars and women are from Venus.
فإنها تبدو في الغالب وكأن الرجال من المريخ والنساء من الزهرة.
But how different are men and women really?
ولكن ما هي الاختلافات الحقيقية بين الرجل والمرأة؟
To find out, let's start by looking at something
لنكتشف ذلك دعونا نبدأ بالنظر إلى أمر
on which men and women really do differ
يختلف فيها الرجل والمرأة فعليًا
and plotting some psychological gender differences on the same scale.
ونضع بعض الاختلافات النفسية حسب الجنس على نفس المقياس.
One thing men and women do really differ on
أحد الأشياء التي يختلف فيها الرجال والنساء
is how far they can throw a ball.
هو مدى إمكانيتهما في رمي الكرة بعيدًا.
So if we look at the data for men here,
لذلك إذا نظرنا إلى بيانات الرجال هنا،
we see what is called a normal distribution curve.
لرأينا ما يسمى منحنى التوزيع الطبيعي.
A few men can throw a ball really far, and a few men not far at all,
يستطيع بعض الرجال رمي الكرة بعيدًا جدًا بينما لا يستطيع قلة آخرون فعل ذلك إطلاقًا،
but most a kind of average distance.
ولكن الأغلب يرمونها لمسافة متوسطة.
And women share the same distribution as well,
وتشترك النساء في نفس التوزيع أيضًا،
but actually there's quite a big difference.
ولكن في الواقع هناك فروق كبيرة.
In fact, the average man can throw a ball further
في الحقيقة، يستطيع الرجل رمي الكرة بمعدل
than about 98 percent of all women.
أكثر بنسبة 98٪ من كل النساء.
So now let's look at what some psychological gender differences
والآن دعونا نرى الاختلافات النفسية بين الجنسين
look like on the same standardized scale.
والتي تبدو متشابهة في نفس المقياس الموحد.
Any psychologist will tell you
سيخبرك أي عالم نفس بأن
that men are better at spatial awareness than women --
الرجال أفضل في الوعي المكاني من النساء --
so things like map-reading, for example -- and it's true,
مثل قراءة الخريطة -- وهي حقيقة،
but let's have a look at the size of this difference.
ولكن دعونا ننظر إلى حجم هذا الاختلاف.
It's tiny; the lines are so close together they almost overlap.
إنه صغير؛ والسطور متقاربة جدًا وكأنها متداخلة.
In fact, the average woman is better than 33 percent of all men,
في الحقيقة، معدل المرأة أفضل بـ 33٪ من كل الرجال،
and of course, if that was 50 percent,
بالطبع لو كانت النسبة 50٪،
then the two genders would be exactly equal.
لكان الجنسان متساويين تمامًا.
It's worth bearing in mind that this difference and the next one I'll show you
يجدر الأخذ بعين الاعتبار أن هذا الاختلاف والاختلاف التالي الذي سأطلعكم عليه
are pretty much the biggest psychological gender differences
هو أكبر الفروقات النفسية بين الجنسين
ever discovered in psychology.
التي تم اكتشافها في علم النفس على الإطلاق.
So here's the next one.
وإليكم الثانية.
Any psychologist will tell you that women are better
أي عالم نفس سيخبركم أن النساء هن الأفضل
with language and grammar than men.
في اللغة والقواعد من الرجال.
So here's performance on the standardized grammar test.
فهنا اختبار الأداء في القواعد المحددة.
There go the women. There go the men.
إليكم معدل النساء. وهنا الرجال.
Again, yes, women are better on average, but the lines are so close
مرة ثانية، نعم، النساء أفضل نسبيًا، ولكن الخطوط قريبة جدًا
that 33 percent of men are better than the average woman,
فـ 33٪ من الرجال أفضل من متوسط النساء،
and again, if it was 50 percent,
ومرة أخرى لو كانت النسبة 50٪،
that would represent complete gender equality.
لكان من شأنها أن تمثل مساواة كاملة بين الجنسين.
It's more a case of, if anything, Mars and Snickers:
إنها أقرب لأن تكون قضية حلوى مارس وسنيكرز:
basically the same, but one's maybe slightly nuttier than the other.
بشكل أساسي هما متماثلان، ولكن أحدهما ربما يكون أغرب من الآخر قليلًا.
I won't say which.
لن أقول أيهما.
Now we've got you warmed up.
الآن وقد تأهبتم.
Let's psychoanalyze you using the famous Rorschach inkblot test.
فدعوني أخضعكم لتحليل نفسي باستخدام اختبار رورسكاش إنكبلوت الشهير.
So you can probably see two, I dunno, two bears or two people or something.
ربما ترون شيئين، أقصد دبين مثلًا، أو شخصين أو شيئًا ما.
But what do you think they're doing?
ولكن ما تظنون أنهم يفعلون؟
Put your hand up if you think they're saying hello.
ارفعوا أيديكم لو تظنون أنهم يقولون مرحبًا.
Put your hands up if you think they are high-fiving.
ارفعوا يدكم لو أنكم تعتقدون أنهما شخصان يضربان كفيهما ببعض فرحًا.
Okay, so if you think they're saying hello or high-fiving,
فقط قلة هناك.
If you think they're fighting,
ولو خمنت أنهما يتشاجران،
you're a bit more of a nasty, aggressive person.
فأنت شخص عدواني وشرير،
Are you a lover or a fighter, basically.
ببساطة هل أنت ودود أم عدواني؟
What about this one?
ماذا عن هذه الصورة ؟
I heard hamster. Who said hamster?
لقد سمعت هامستر. من قال هامستر؟
A guy there said hamster.
الشاب هناك قال هامستر.
Well, you should see some kind of two-legged animal here,
حسنًا، ينبغي أن ترى نوعًا من الحيوانات ذوات الأرجل هنا،
If you didn't, then this means that you have difficulty
إن لم يكن كذلك، فهذا يعني أنك تعاني من صعوبة
processing complex situations where there's a lot going on.
في معالجة المواقف المعقدة التي تحدث فيها أمور كثيرة.
Except, of course, it doesn't mean that at all.
إلا أن هذا بالطبع ليس صحيحًا على الإطلاق.
Rorschach inkblot tests have basically no validity
اختبارات رورسكاش إنكبلوت ليس لها أساس من الصحة
when it comes to diagnosing people's personality
عندما يتعلق الأمر بتحليل شخصية الناس
and are not used by modern-day psychologists.
ولا يستخدمها علماء النفس في العصر الحديث.
In fact, one recent study found that when you do try
في الحقيقة، وجدت أحد الدراسات مؤخرًا أنك عندما تحاول
to diagnose people's personalities using Rorschach inkblot tests,
تحليل شخصيات الناس باستخدام ذلك الاختبار،
schizophrenia was diagnosed
فسيتم تشخيص مرض الفصام
in about one sixth of apparently perfectly normal participants.
فيما يقارب سدس المشاركين الأسوياء تمامًا.
maybe you are not a very visual type of person.
ربما لأنك لست من الأشخاص البصريين كثيرًا.
So let's do another quick quiz to find out.
لذا دعونا الآن نقوم باختبار آخر لنرى.
When making a cake, do you prefer to -- so hands up for each one again --
وأنت تصنع الحلوى ماذا تفضل --ارفع يدك لكل تصويت كذلك --
do you prefer to use a recipe book with pictures?
هل تفضل استخدام كتاب الوصفة مع صور؟
Have a friend talk you through?
أو أن يشرح لك صديقك عنها؟
Or have a go, making it up as you go along?
أو تجرب وتصنعها كما يحلو لك؟
Quite a few people there.
فقط قلة هناك.
Okay, so if you said A,
حسنًا، لو كان جوابك الاحتمال الأول،
then this means that you are a visual learner
فهذا يعني أنك متعلم بصري
If you said B, it means you're an auditory learner,
ولو اخترت الخيار الثاني فهذا يعني أنك متعلم سمعي،
that you learn best when information is presented to you in an auditory format.
تتعلم بشكل أفضل عندما تقدم لك المعلومة بشكل صوتي.
And if you said C, it means that you're a kinesthetic learner,
ولو اخترت الخيار الثالث فيعني أنك متعلم حركي،
that you learn best when you get stuck in and do things with your hands.
تتعلم بشكل أفضل عندما تتعثر وتجرب بيديك.
Except, of course, as you've probably guessed,
ما عدا، بالطبع، كما تعتقدون على الأرجح أنه
that it doesn't, because the whole thing is a complete myth.
غير صحيح، لأن الحكاية كلها هي محض خرافة.
So we know this because in tightly controlled experimental studies,
إذًا نحن نعلم ذلك لأنه في الدراسات التجريبية المحدودة،
when learners are given material to learn
عندما تُقدَّم المادة للمتعلم
either in their preferred style or an opposite style,
سواء بالطريقة التي يفضلها أم لا،
it makes no difference at all to the amount of information that they retain.
فإنها لا تؤثر على الإطلاق في كمية المعلومات التي يحفظها.
And if you think about it for just a second,
ولو فكرتم في ذلك لبرهة،
it's just obvious that this has to be true.
لاتضح لكم صحة ذلك.
It's obvious that the best presentation format
فمن الواضح أن أنسب طرق التقديم
depends not on you, but on what you're trying to learn.
لا تعتمد عليك بحجم اعتمادها على المادة التي تحاول تعلمها.
Could you learn to drive a car, for example,
هل بإمكانك تعلم قيادة السيارة مثلًا
just by listening to someone telling you what to do
من خلال الاستماع إلى تعليمات من حولك فحسب
with no kinesthetic experience?
ومن دون أي تطبيق عملي؟
Could you solve simultaneous equations
هل يمكنك حل معادلات بشكل فوري
by talking them through in your head and without writing them down?
من خلال تحليلها في عقلك دون اللجوء لكتابتها؟
Could you revise for your architecture exams
هل يمكنك أن تحضر لامتحان هندسة معمارية
using interpretive dance if you're a kinesthetic learner?
باللجوء إلى الرقص التفسيري، لو كنت متعلمًا حسيًا؟
No. What you need to do is match the material to be learned
لا، ما تحتاجه هو الربط بين المادة التي تتعلمها
to the presentation format, not you.
وبين طريقة العرض، وليس الربط معك.
I know many of you are A-level students
أعرف أن أغلبكم طلاب في المستوى A
that will have recently gotten your GCSE results.
وحصلتم مؤخرًا على نتائجكم في اختبار الثانوية.
And if you didn't quite get what you were hoping for,
فإذا لم تكن نتيجتك كما تأملت
then you can't really blame your learning style,
عندها لا يمكنك أن تلقي باللوم على طريقة التعليم،
but one thing that you might want to think about blaming is your genes.
بل على شيء واحد وهو جيناتك.
So what this is all about is a recent study at University College London
كل ذلك هو عبارة عن دراسة أجرتها جامعة كولج لندن
found that 58 percent of the variation
التي أظهرت أن 58٪ من الاختلافات
between different students and their GCSE results
بين الطلبة ونتائج اختباراتهم في امتحان الثانوية العامة
was down to genetic factors.
يعود لعوامل جينية.
That sounds like a very precise figure, so how can we tell?
يبدو كأنه رقم دقيق جدًا، إذًا كيف يمكننا الاستدلال عليه؟
Well, when we want to unpack the relative contributions
حسنا،عندما نريد فك المساهمات النسبية
of genes and the environment,
للبيئة والجينات،
what we can do is do a twin study.
ما يمكننا القيام به هو دراسة التوائم.
So identical twins share 100 percent of their environment
فالتوائم الحقيقية تتقاسم 100٪ نفس البيئة
and 100 percent of their genes,
و 100٪ من نفس الجينات،
whereas non-identical twins share 100 percent of their environment,
بينما التوائم الكاذبة يتشاركون 100٪ نفس البيئة
So by comparing how similar GCSE results are in identical twins
فبمقارنة مدى تشابه نتائج اختبار الثانوية في التوائم الحقيقية
versus non-identical twins,
مقارنة بالتوائم الكاذبة،
and doing some clever math,
وببعض العمليات الحسابية الذكية،
we can an idea of how much variation and performance is due to the environment
نستطيع الوصول إلى معرفة مدى تأثر الاختلاف والأداء تبعًا للبيئة
and how much is due to genes.
وكم منها يعود إلى الجينات.
And it turns out that it's about 58 percent due to genes.
واتضح أن 58٪ هو بسبب للجينات.
So this isn't to undermine the hard work that you and your teachers here put in.
لا يدعو هذا للتقليل من جهدك أو جهد المعلم.
If you didn't quite get the GCSE results that you were hoping for,
إن لم تكن نتائجك مرضية في اختبار الثانوية،
then you can always try blaming your parents, or at least their genes.
عندها حاول أن تلوم والديك، أو على الأقل جيناتهم.
One thing that you shouldn't blame
شيء واحد لا يمكنه لومه
is being a left-brained or right-brained learner,
هو إذا كنت تستعمل الفص الأيمن أو الأيسر من الدماغ أثناء التعلم،
because again, this is a myth.
مرة ثانية، لأن هذه خرافة.
So the myth here is that the left brain is logical,
إذاً الخرافة هنا أن الفص الأيسر منطقي،
it's good with equations like this,
يفيد في معادلات كهذه،
and the right brain is more creative, so the right brain is better at music.
والفص الأيمن إبداعي أكثر، ويفيد أكثر في الموسيقى.
But again, this is a myth because nearly everything that you do
ولكن مرة ثانية، إنها خرافة لأن كل ما تفعله تقريبًا
involves nearly all parts of your brain talking together,
يشتغل فيه كل أجزاء عقلك تقريبًا.
However, perhaps one reason why this myth has survived
ومع ذلك، ربما هناك سبب واحد وراء صمود هذه الخرافة
is that there is a slight grain of truth to it.
وهو أنها تحوي على شيء ضئيل من الحقيقة.
So a related version of the myth
هناك رؤية لصيقة بهذه الخرافة
which kind of makes sense because your brain controls the opposite hands,
وهو أمر منطقي نوعًا ما لأن دماغك يتحكم بعكس اليد المستخدمة،
so left-handed people,
فالأشخاص العسراويون،
the right side of the brain is slightly more active
يكون عندهم الفص الأيمن من الدماغ أنشط
than the left-hand side of the brain,
من الفص الأيسر،
Now, it isn't true per se
هذا ليس صحيحًا في حد ذاته
that left-handed people are more creative than right-handed people.
بأن الأشخاص العسراويين هم أكثر إبداعًا من الأيامن.
What is true that ambidextrous people,
الصحيح هنا هو أن الأشخاص المبدعين،
or people who use both hands for different tasks,
أو الذين يستخدمون كلتا يديهم لأداء مهام مختلفة،
are more creative thinkers than one-handed people,
يحملون تفكيرًا أكثر إبداعًا من الذين يستخدمون يدًا واحدة،
because being ambidextrous involves
لأن كونك تستخدم كلتا يديك فهذا يعني
having both sides of the brain talk to each other a lot,
أن فصي دماغك يعملان سوية
which seems to be involved in creating flexible thinking.
مما يساعد على خلق تفكير مرن.
The myth of the creative left-hander
الخرافة في إبداع اليد اليسرى
arises from the fact that being ambidextrous
نشأت من الحقيقة بأن الموهوبين
is more common amongst left-handers than right-handers,
أكثر شيوعًا في أوساط العسراويين منهم عند الأيامن،
so a grain of truth in the idea of the creative left-hander,
فهناك شيء ضئيل من الحقيقة في فكرة إبداع العسراويين،
but not much.
ولكن ليس كثيراً.
is that we only use 10 percent of our brains.
هي أننا نستخدم فقط 10٪من دماغنا.
This is, again, a complete myth.
مرة أخرى، إنها محض خرافة.
uses nearly all of our brains.
نستخدم فيه تقريبًا كل دماغنا.
that most of us don't use our brainpower quite as well as we could.
بأن معظمنا لا يستخدم كل قدراته العقلية مع أنهم يقدرون على ذلك.
So what could we do to boost our brainpower?
ما الذي يمكننا القيام به لتعزيز قدراتنا العقلية؟
Maybe we could listen to a nice bit of Mozart.
ربما يمكننا الاستماع إلى موزارت قليلًا.
Have you heard of the idea of the Mozart effect?
هل سمعتم بفكرة تأثير موزارت؟
So the idea is that listening to Mozart makes you smarter
الفكرة هي سماعك لموزارت يجعلك أكثر ذكاءًا
and improves your performance on I.Q. tests.
ويحسن مستوى أدائك في اختبار نسبة الذكاء.
is that although it's basically a myth, there is a grain of truth to it.
هو أنها على الرغم بأنها خرافة أساسًا إلا أنها تحتوي شيئًا من الحقيقة.
So the original study found that
فالدراسة الأصلية أظهرت أن
did better on a subsequent I.Q. test
كان أداؤهم أفضل في اختبار نسبة الذكاء
than participants who simply sat in silence.
من المشاركين الذين جلسوا في صمت.
But a follow-up study recruited some people who liked Mozart music
ولكن في دراسة متممة تطوع عدد من الأشخاص من محبي موزارت
and then another group of people
وعدد آخر من المعجبين
who were fans of the horror stories of Stephen King.
بالقصص المرعبة لـ ستيفن كينغ.
And they played the people the music or the stories.
وبدؤوا بسماع الموسيقى أو القصص.
The people who preferred Mozart music to the stories
حصل الأشخاص الذين فضلوا الموسيقى على القصص
got a bigger I.Q. boost from the Mozart than the stories,
على تحفيز أكثر في اختبار نسبة الذكاء من سماعهم الموسيقى أكثر من القصص،
but the people who preferred the stories to the Mozart music
في حين أن الأشخاص الذين فضلوا القصص على الموسيقى
got a bigger I.Q. boost from listening to the Stephen King stories
تلقوا التحفيز في اختبار نسبة الذكاء في سماعهم للقصص
than the Mozart music.
أكثر من سماعهم لموسيقى موزارت.
So the truth is that listening to something that you enjoy
ففي الحقيقة استماعك لشيء تستمتع به
perks you up a bit and gives you a temporary I.Q. boost
يشجعك قليلًا ويمنحك حافزًا مؤقتًا في اختبار الذكاء
on a narrow range of tasks.
على نطاق ضيق من المهام.
There's no suggestion that listening to Mozart,
ليس هناك أية إشارات بأن استماعك لموزارت،
is going to make you any smarter in the long run.
سيجعلك ذكيًا على المدى البعيد.
Another version of the Mozart myth
نسخة أخرى لخرافة موسيقى موزارت
is that listening to Mozart can make you not only cleverer but healthier, too.
هي أن استماعك لها ليس فقط يجعلك أذكى وإنما أكثر صحة كذلك.
Unfortunately, this doesn't seem to be true
للأسف لا يبدو ذلك صحيحًا
of someone who listened to the music of Mozart almost every day,
من شخص استمع لموزارت كل يوم تقريبًا،
Mozart himself,
وهو موزارت نفسه
who suffered from gonorrhea, smallpox, arthritis,
الذي عانى من مرض السيلان والجدري والتهاب المفاصل،
and, what most people think eventually killed him in the end, syphilis.
ومن المرض الذي قتله في النهاية، بحسب ما يعتقد الناس، وهو الزهري.
This suggests that Mozart should have bit more careful, perhaps,
يشير ذلك إلى أنه كان ينبغي على موزارت أن يكون حذراً أكثر
when choosing his sexual partners.
ربما، في اختيار شريك حياته.
But how do we choose a partner?
ولكن كيف نختار شريكنا؟
So a myth that I have to say is sometimes spread a bit by sociologists
عليَّ أن أذكر خرافة منتشرة بين أوساط علماء الاجتماع
is that our preferences in a romantic partner are a product of our culture,
بأن ما نفضله في شريكنا هو نتاجٌ لثقافتنا،
that they're very culturally specific.
أي أن اختياراتنا ذات خاصية ثقافية.
But in fact, the data don't back this up.
ولكن في الحقيقة، المعطيات لا تشير إلى ذلك.
A famous study surveyed people from [37] different cultures across the globe,
أجريت دراسة مشهورة على أشخاص ينحدرون من 37 ثقافة مختلفة من كافة أنحاء العالم،
from Americans to Zulus,
من الأمريكيين إلى الزولو،
on what they look for in a partner.
عن ماذا يفضلون في الشريك.
And in every single culture across the globe,
وفي كل الثقافات حول العالم،
men placed more value on physical attractiveness in a partner
أعطى الرجال قيمة أعلى لجاذبية الجسد
than did women,
أكثر مما أعطته النساء،
and in every single culture, too,
وكذلك في كل الثقافات،
women placed more importance than did men on ambition and high earning power.
أعطت النساء أهمية أكثر من الرجال للطموح وقدرات للكسب.
In every culture, too,
وأيضاً في كل الثقافات،
men preferred women who were younger than themselves,
فضّل الرجال النساء اللاتي أصغر منهم سنًا
an average of, I think it was 2.66 years,
بمعدل تقريبي 2.66 سنة.
and in every culture, too,
وفي كل الثقافات كذلك،
women preferred men who were older than them,
فضلت النساء الرجال الأكبر منهن سنًا.
so an average of 3.42 years,
بمعدل 3.42 سنة.
which is why we've got here "Everybody needs a Sugar Daddy."
لهذا السبب هنا عندنا "كل شخص يريد أبًا معطاءًا."
to trying to score in basketball or football or whatever your sport is.
إلى محاولة تحقيق الهدف في مباراة لكرة السلة أو القدم أو أيًا تكن رياضتك.
The myth here is that sportsmen go through hot-hand streaks, Americans call them,
الخرافة هنا أن الرياضي يتلاعب بالأوراق الرابحة، كما يسميها الأمريكان،
or purple patches, we sometimes say in England,
أو ضربات حظ، كما نسميها أحيانًا في إنجلترا،
where they just can't miss, like this guy here.
حيث أنهم لا يخطئون، كما هو حال هذا الشاب هنا.
But in fact, what happens is that if you analyze the pattern
ولكن في الحقيقة، ما يحدث هو أنك إن قمت بتحليل قالب
of hits and misses statistically,
الإصابات الصحيحة والأخطاء بشكل إحصائي،
it turns out that it's nearly always at random.
فإنه يتضح أنها تقريبًا عشوائية.
Your brain creates patterns from the randomness.
ويقوم دماغك بإنشاء القوالب من العشوائية.
If you toss a coin,
إن رميت قطعة نقود،
a streak of heads or tails is going to come out somewhere in the randomness,
فإن شريطًا من الوجوه العلوية أو السفلية سيظهر ضمن الضربات العشوائية،
and because the brain likes to see patterns where there are none,
ولأن دماغك يحب أن يرى القوالب في أماكن لا توجد بها،
we look at these streaks and attribute meanings to them
نحن ننظر إلى هذه الشرائط من الأحداث ونربطها بمعانٍ
and say, "Yeah he's really on form today,"
ونقول "نعم، إنه اليوم بوضعية جيدة"،
whereas actually you would get the same pattern
في حين أنك في الحقيقة تحصل على القالب ذاته
if you were just getting hits and misses at random.
إن كنت تحصل على الإصابات والأخطاء بشكل عشوائي.
So an exception to this, however, is penalty shootouts.
إذًا فالاستثناء لهذا، على أية حال، هو ضربات الجزاء.
A recent study looking at penalty shootouts in football
أظهرت دراسة حديثة تلاحظ ضربات الجزاء في لعبة كرة القدم
shows that players who represent countries
أن اللاعبين الذين يمثلون دولًا
with a very bad record in penalty shootouts,
ذات سجل سيء جدًا في ضربات الجزاء،
like, for example, England,
مثل إنجلترا، على سبيل المثال،
tend to be quicker to take their shots than countries with a better record,
تميل إلى أخذ ضرباتها بشكل أسرع من غيرها من الدول ذات السجل الأفضل،
and presumably as a result, they're more likely to miss.
وكنتيجة لذلك على ما يبدو، فهم من المرجح أكثر ألا يصيبوا الهدف.
Which raises the question
مما يثير سؤالًا
of if there's any way that we could improve people's performance.
عما إن كانت هناك طريقة نستطيع من خلالها تحسين أداء الناس.
And one thing you might think about doing
وأحد الأشياء التي ربما تفكرون بالقيام بها
is punishing people for their misses and seeing if that improves them.
هو معاقبة الناس لأخطائهم ومشاهدة فيما إن كان ذلك يحسن من مستواهم.
This idea, the effect that punishment can improve performance,
هذه الفكرة، تأثير العقاب يمكن أن يحسن الأداء،
is what participants thought they were testing
هي ما اعتقد المشاركون أنهم يختبرون
in Milgram's famous learning and punishment experiment
في تجربة اختبار ملغرام للتعليم والعقاب
that you've probably heard about if you're a psychology student.
التي ربما قد سمعتم عنها إن كنتم تلامذة علم نفس.
The story goes that participants were prepared to give
في تفاصيل القصة كان المشاركون جاهزين لإعطاء
what they believed to be fatal electric shocks to a fellow participant
ما اعتقدوا أنها صدمات كهربية مميتة إلى زملاء مشاركين
when they got a question wrong,
عندما أجابواعن سؤال بإجابة خاطئة،
just because someone in a white coat told them to.
فقط لأن شخصًا يرتدي بزة بيضاء أخبرهم بأن يفعلوا ذلك.
But this story is a myth for three reasons.
ولكن هذه القصة خرافة لثلاثة أسباب:
Firstly and most crucially, the lab coat wasn't white, it was in fact grey.
الأول والأكثر أهمية، لم تكن بزة المختبر بيضاء، ولكنها في الحقيقة كانت رمادية.
Secondly, the participants were told before the study
الثاني، أُخبر المشاركون قبل الدراسة
and reminded any time they raised a concern,
وذكِّروا كلما زادت مخاوفهم
that although the shocks were painful, they were not fatal
بأنه على الرغم من كون الصدمات مؤلمة، فإنها لم تكن مميتة
and indeed caused no permanent damage whatsoever.
وبالفعل لم تسبب أي أذىً دائم إطلاقًا.
And thirdly, participants didn't give the shocks
الثالث: لم يعط المشاركون الصدمات
just because someone in the coat told them to.
فقط لأن شخصًا ما يرتدي بزةً أخبرهم بذلك.
When they were interviewed after the study,
وعندما تمت مقابلتهم بعد الدراسة،
all the participants said that they firmly believed
قال جميع المشاركين بأنهم آمنوا بشدة
that the learning and punishment study served a worthy scientific purpose
بأن دراسة التعليم والعقاب خدمت هدفًا ذا قيمة علمية
which would have enduring gains for science
سيكون لها فوائد مستمرة على صعيد العلم
as opposed to the momentary nonfatal discomfort caused to the participants.
على العكس من الانزعاج اللحظي غير المميت الذي أصيب به المشاركون.
Okay, so I've been talking for about 12 minutes now,
حسنًا، لقد تكلمت لمدة 12 دقيقة الآن،
and you've probably been sitting there listening to me,
وربما أنتم جالسون هنالك تستمعون إليَّ،
analyzing my speech patterns and body language
وتحللون نمط حديثي ولغة جسمي
and trying to work out if you should take any notice of what I'm saying,
وتحاولون استيعاب فيما إذا كان عليكم أخذ أي ملاحظة عما أقوله،
whether I'm telling the truth or whether I'm lying,
سواءًا كنت أخبركم الحقيقة أم كنت أكذب،
but if so you've probably completely failed,
ولكن إن كان الأمر كذلك فربما تكونون فشلتم بالكامل،
because although we all think we can catch a liar
فبالرغم من أننا نعتقد بأننا نستطيع الإمساك بكاذب
from their body language and speech patterns,
من لغة الجسم وقوالب الكلام،
hundreds of psychological tests over the years have shown
إلا أن مئات الاختبارات النفسية قد أظهرت على مر السنين
that all of us, including police officers and detectives,
بأننا جميعًا، بمن فينا الشرطة والمحققين،
are basically at chance when it comes to detecting lies from body language
ببساطة تجمعنا الصدفة عند كشف الكذب من خلال لغة الجسم
and verbal patterns.
وقوالب الكلام.
Interestingly, there is one exception:
وبشكل مثير للاهتمام، هناك استثناء واحد:
TV appeals for missing relatives.
المناشدات المتلفزة للأشخاص المفقودين.
It's quite easy to predict when the relatives are missing
من السهل تمامًا التنبؤ عند فقد الأقارب
and when the appealers have in fact murdered the relatives themselves.
وعند قتل المناشدين للأقارب بأنفسهم.
So hoax appealers are more likely to shake their heads, to look away,
فمن الأرجح أن المناشدين الماكرين يهزون رؤوسهم، للنظر بعيدًا،
and to make errors in their speech,
وكي يخطئوا في حديثهم،
whereas genuine appealers are more likely
حيث أن المناشدين الصادقين من الأرجح
to express hope that the person will return safely
أن يقوموا بالتعبير عن الأمل بأن الشخص سيعود سالمًا
and to avoid brutal language.
وأن يجتنبوا اللغة الهمجية.
So, for example, they might say "taken from us" rather than "killed."
إذُا، على سبيل المثال، ربما يقولون "المخطوفين منا" بدل "المقتولين."
Speaking of which, it's about time I killed this talk,
وبالمناسبة، تبقى القليل من الوقت لإنهائي هذه المحادثة،
but before I do, I just want to give you in 30 seconds
ولكن قبل فعل ذلك، أريد إعطءكم في 30 ثانية
the overarching myth of psychology.
الخرافة الشاملة في علم النفس.
So the myth is that psychology is just a collection of interesting theories,
إذًا فالخرافة هي أن علم النفس هو مجموعة من النظريات الممتعة فحسب،
all of which say something useful and all of which have something to offer.
كلها تقول شيئًا مفيدًا وتقدم شيئًا ما.
What I hope to have shown you in the past few minutes
ما آمل أن أكون قد أريتكم إياه خلال الدقائق القليلة الماضية
is that this isn't true.
هو أن ذلك ليس صحيحًا.
What we need to do is assess psychological theories
ما نحتاج لفعله هو تقييم النظريات النفسية
by seeing what predictions they make,
من خلال رؤية التنبؤات التي تُحدثها،
whether that is that listening to Mozart makes you smarter,
سواء كان الاستماع إلى موزارت يجعلكم أذكى،
that you learn better when information is presented in your preferred learning style
أنكم تتعلمون بشكل أفضل عندما تُقدم المعلومات بطريقة التعليم المفضلة لديكم
or whatever it is, all of these are testable empirical predictions,
أم غير ذلك، من كل هذه التنبؤات التجريبية الاختبارية،
and the only way we can make progress
والطريقة الوحيدة التي يمكننا أن نحرز من خلالها تقدمًا
in tightly controlled experimental studies.
بدراسات تجريبية محكمة للغاية.
And it's only by doing so that we can hope to discover
من خلال ذلك فحسب يمكننا أن نأمل باكتشاف
which of these theories are well supported,
أي هذه النظريات مدعومة بشكل جيد،
and which, like all the ones I've told you about today, are myths.
وأيها، ككل تلك النظريات التي أخبرتكم عنها اليوم، محض خرافات.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)